As you can probably tell by now the
bulk of this series is on understanding matrix
and vector operations through that more visual lens
of linear transformations.
This video is no exception, describing the concepts
of inverse matrices, column space, rank, and, null
space through that lens.
A forewarning though, I'm not gonna talk about
the methods for actually computing these things, and
some would argue that that's pretty important. There
are a lot of very good resources for
learning those methods outside this series. Keywords, Gaussian
elimination and row echelon form. I think most
of the value that I actually have to
add here is on the intuition half.
Plus, in practice, we usually get software to
compute this stuff for us anyway.
First, a few words on the usefulness of
linear algebra. By now you already have a
hint for how it's used in describing the
manipulation of space, which is useful for things
like computer graphics and robotics.
But one of the main reasons that linear
algebra is more broadly applicable and required for
just about any technical discipline is that it
lets us solve certain systems of equations.
When I say system of equations, I mean
you have a list of variables, things you
don't know, and a list of equations relating
them.
In a lot of situations,
those equations can get very complicated.
But if you're lucky, they might take on
a certain special form.
Within each equation,
the only thing happening to each variable is
that it's scaled by some constant,
and the only thing happening to each of
those scaled variables is that they're added to
each other.
So no exponents or fancy functions are multiplying
two variables together, things like that.
The typical way to organize this sort of
special system of equations is to throw all
the variables on the left
and put any lingering constants on the right.
It's also nice to vertically line up the
common variables, and to do that, you might
need to throw in some zero coefficients whenever
the variable doesn't show up in one of
the equations.
This is called a linear system of equations.
You might notice that this looks a lot
like matrix vector multiplication.
In fact, you can package all of the
equations together into a single vector equation where
you have the matrix containing all of the
constant coefficients and a vector containing all of
the variables,
and their matrix vector product equals some different
constant vector.
Let's name that constant matrix A, denote the
vector holding the variables with a bold faced
x,
and call the constant vector on the right
hand side v.
This is more than just a notational trick
to get our system of equations written on
one line. It sheds light on a pretty
cool geometric interpretation for the problem.
The matrix A corresponds with some linear transformation.
So solving A x equals v means we're
looking for a vector x,
which after applying the transformation
lands on v.
Think about what's happening here for a moment.
You can hold in your head this really
complicated idea of multiple variables all intermingling with
each other just by thinking about squishing and
morphing space and trying to figure out which
vector lands on another. Cool, right?
To start simple, let's say you have a
system with two equations and two unknowns.
This means the matrix A is a two
by two matrix and v and x are
each two dimensional vectors.
Now, how we think about the solutions to
this equation depends on whether the transformation associated
with a squishes all of space into a
lower dimension like a line or a point,
or if it leaves everything spanning the full
two dimensions where it started.
In the language of the last video, we
subdivide into the cases where A has zero
determinant and the case where A has non
zero determinant.
Let's start with the most likely case where
the determinant is non zero, meaning space does
not get squished into a zero area region.
In this case, there will always be one
and only one vector that lands on v
and you can find it by playing the
transformation in reverse.
Following where v goes as we rewind the
tape like this, you'll find the vector x
such that a times x equals v.
When you play the transformation in reverse, it
actually corresponds to a separate linear transformation commonly
called the inverse of a, denoted a to
the negative one.
For example, if A was a counterclockwise rotation
by 90 degrees, then the inverse of A
would be a clockwise rotation by 90 degrees.
If A was a rightward shear that pushes
j hat one unit to the right, the
inverse of A would be a leftward shear
that pushes j hat one unit to the
left.
In general, A inverse is the unique transformation
with the property that if you first apply
A, then follow it with the transformation A
inverse, you end up back where you started.
Applying one transformation after another is captured algebraically
with matrix multiplication.
So the core property of this transformation A
inverse is that A inverse times A
equals the matrix that corresponds to doing nothing.
The transformation that does nothing is called the
identity transformation.
It leaves I hat and j hat each
where they are, unmoved, so its columns are
one zero and zero one.
Once you find this inverse, which in practice
you do with a computer,
you can solve your equation by multiplying this
inverse matrix by V.
And again, what this means geometrically
is that you're playing the transformation in reverse
and following V.
This non zero determinant case, which for a
random choice of matrix is by far the
most likely one, corresponds with the idea that
if you have two unknowns and two equations,
it's almost certainly the case that there's a
single unique solution.
This idea also makes sense in higher dimensions
when the number of equations equals the number
of unknowns.
Again, the system of equations can be translated
to the geometric interpretation
where you have some transformation a
and some vector v and you're looking for
the vector x that lands on v.
As long as the transformation A doesn't squish
all of space into a lower dimension, meaning
its determinant is non zero, there will be
an inverse transformation,
A inverse, with the property that if you
first do A, then you do A inverse,
it's the same as doing nothing.
And to solve your equation, you just have
to multiply that reverse transformation matrix by the
vector v.
But when the determinant is zero and the
transformation associated with the system of equations squishes
space into a smaller dimension,
there is no inverse. You cannot un squish
a line to turn it into a plane.
At least that's not something that a function
can do. That would require transforming each individual
vector into a whole line full of vectors.
But functions can only take a single input
to a single output.
Similarly,
for three equations and three unknowns, there will
be no inverse if the corresponding transformation
squishes three d space onto the plane or
even if it squishes it onto a line
or a point.
Those all correspond to a determinant of zero
since any region is squished into something with
zero volume.
It's still possible that a solution exists even
when there is no inverse. It's just that
when your transformation squishes space onto, say, a
line, you have to be lucky enough that
the vector v lives somewhere on that line.
You might notice that some of these zero
determinant cases feel a lot more restrictive than
others. Given a three by three matrix, for
example, it seems a lot harder for a
solution to exist when it squishes space onto
a line compared to when it squishes things
onto a plane, even though both of those
are zero determinant.
We have some language that's a bit more
specific than just saying zero determinant.
When the output of a transformation is a
line, meaning it's one dimensional,
we say the transformation has a rank of
one.
If all the vectors land on some two
dimensional plane, we say the transformation has a
rank of two.
So the word rank means the number of
dimensions in the output of a transformation.
For instance, in the case of two by
two matrices, rank two is the best that
it can be. It means the basis vectors
continue to span the full two dimensions of
space and the determinant is non zero. But
for three by three matrices,
rank two means that we've collapsed,
but not as much as they would have
collapsed for a rank one situation.
If a three d transformation
has a non zero determinant and its output
fills all of three d space, it has
a rank of three.
This set of all possible outputs for your
matrix, whether it's a line, a plane, three
d space, whatever,
is called the column space of your matrix.
You can probably guess where that name comes
from. The columns of your matrix tell you
where the basis vectors land,
and the span of those transformed basis vectors
gives you all possible outputs.
In other words, the column space is the
span of the columns of your matrix.
So a more precise definition of rank would
be that it's the number of dimensions in
the column space.
When this rank is as high as it
can be, meaning it equals the number of
columns, we call the matrix full rank.
Notice, the zero vector will always be included
in the column space since linear transformations must
keep the origin fixed in place.
For a full rank transformation,
the only vector that lands at the origin
is the zero vector itself.
But for matrices that aren't full rank, which
squished to a smaller dimension, you can have
a whole bunch of vectors land on zero.
If a two d transformation squishes space onto
a line, for example, there is a separate
line in a different direction full of vectors
that get squished onto the origin.
If a three d transformation squishes space onto
a plane, there's also a full line of
vectors that land on the origin.
If a three d transformation squishes all of
space onto a line, then there's a whole
plane full of vectors that land on the
origin.
This set of vectors that lands on the
origin is called the null space or the
kernel of your matrix. It's the space of
all vectors that become null in the sense
that they land on the zero vector.
In terms of the linear system of equations,
when v happens to be the zero vector,
the null space gives you all of the
possible solutions to the equation.
So that's a very high level overview of
how to think about linear systems of equations
geometrically.
Each system has some kind of linear transformation
associated with it. And when that transformation has
an inverse, you can use that inverse to
solve your system.
Otherwise,
the idea of column space lets us understand
when a solution even exists.
And the idea of a null space helps
us to understand what the set of all
possible solutions can look like.
Again, there's a lot that I haven't covered
here, most notably how to compute these things.
I also had to limit my scope to
examples where the number of equations equals the
number of unknowns.
But the goal here is not to try
to teach everything, it's that you come away
with a strong intuition for inverse matrices, column
space, and null space, and that those intuitions
make any future learning that you do more
fruitful.
Next video, by popular request, will be a
brief footnote about non square matrices,
then after that I'm going to give you
my take on dot products and something pretty
cool that happens when you view them under
the light of linear transformations.
See you then.