Hey, everyone. If I had to choose just
one topic that makes all of the others
in linear algebra start to click and which
too often goes unlearned the first time a
student takes linear algebra, it would be this
one. The idea of a linear transformation and
its relation to matrices.
For this video, I'm just gonna focus on
what these transformations look like in the case
of two dimensions and how they relate to
the idea of matrix vector multiplication.
In particular, I wanna show you a way
to think about matrix vector multiplication
that doesn't rely on memorization.
To start, let's just parse this term, linear
transformation.
Transformation is essentially a fancy word for function.
It's something that takes in inputs and spits
out an output for each one. Specifically, in
the context of linear algebra, we like to
think about transformations that take in some vector
and spit out another vector.
So why use the word transformation instead of
function if they mean the same thing?
Well, it's to be suggestive of a certain
way to visualize this input output relation. You
see, a great way to understand functions of
vectors is to use movement.
If a transformation takes some input vector to
some output vector,
we imagine that input vector moving over to
the output vector.
Then to understand the transformation as a whole,
we might imagine watching every possible input vector
move over to its corresponding output vector.
It gets really crowded to think about all
of the vectors all at once, each one
as an arrow. So as I mentioned last
video, a nice trick is to conceptualize each
vector not as an arrow, but as a
single point, the point where its tip sits.
That way, to think about a transformation taking
every possible input vector to some output vector,
we watch every point in space moving to
some other point.
In the case of transformations in two dimensions,
to get a better feel for the whole
shape of the transformation,
I like to do this with all of
the points on an infinite grid.
I also sometimes like to keep a copy
of the grid in the background just to
help keep track of where everything ends up
relative to where it starts.
The effect for various transformations moving around all
of the points in space is, you've gotta
admit, beautiful.
It gives the feeling of squishing and morphing
space itself.
As you can imagine though, arbitrary transformations
can look pretty complicated.
But luckily, linear algebra limits itself to a
special type of transformation,
ones that are easier to understand called linear
transformations.
Visually speaking, a transformation is linear if it
has two properties.
All lines must remain lines without getting curved,
and the origin must remain fixed in place.
For example, this right here would not be
a linear transformation since the lines get all
curvy.
And this one right here, although it keeps
the line straight,
is not a linear transformation because it moves
the origin.
This one here fixes the origin, and it
might look like it keeps lines straight, but
that's just because I'm only showing the horizontal
and vertical grid lines. When you see what
it does to a diagonal line, it becomes
clear that it's not at all linear since
it turns that line all curvy.
In general, you should think of linear transformations
as keeping grid lines parallel
and evenly spaced.
Some linear transformations are simple to think about,
like rotations about the origin.
Others are a little trickier to describe with
words.
So how do you think you could describe
these transformations
numerically?
If you were, say, programming some animations to
make a video teaching the topic, what formula
do you give the computer so that if
you give it the coordinates of a vector,
it can give you the coordinates of where
that vector lands?
It turns out that you only need to
record where the two basis vectors I hat
and j hat each land,
and everything else will follow from that.
For example, consider the vector v with coordinates
negative one, two, meaning that it equals negative
one times I hat plus two times j
hat.
If we play some transformation and follow where
all three of these vectors go,
the property that grid lines remain parallel and
evenly spaced has a really important consequence.
The place where v lands will be negative
one times the vector where I hat landed
plus two times the vector where j hat
landed.
In other words, it started off as a
certain linear combination of I hat and j
hat, and it ends up as that same
linear combination of where those two vectors landed.
This means you can deduce where v must
go based only on where I hat and
j hat each land.
This is why I like keeping a copy
of the original grid in the background. For
the transformation shown here, we can read off
that I hat lands on the coordinates one,
negative two, and j hat lands on the
x axis over at the coordinates three, zero.
This means that the vector represented by negative
one I hat plus two times j hat
ends up at negative one times the vector
one, negative two,
plus two times the vector three, zero.
Adding that altogether,
you can deduce that it has to land
on the vector five, two.
This is a good point to pause and
ponder because it's pretty important.
Now given that I'm actually showing you the
full transformation,
you could have just looked to see that
v has the coordinates five two.
But the cool part here is that this
gives us a technique to deduce where any
vectors land so long as we have a
record of where I hat and j hat
each land without needing to watch the transformation
itself.
Write the vector with more general coordinates x
and y,
and it will land on x times the
vector where I hat lands, one negative two,
plus y times the vector where j hat
lands, three zero.
Carrying out that sum, you see that it
lands at one x plus three y,
negative two x plus zero y.
I give you any vector, and you can
tell me where that vector lands using this
formula.
What all of this is saying is that
a two dimensional linear transformation
is completely described by just four numbers,
the two coordinates for where I hat lands
and the two coordinates for where j hat
lands.
Isn't that cool?
It's common to package these coordinates into a
two by two grid of numbers called a
two by two matrix,
where you can interpret the columns as the
two special vectors where I hat and j
hat each land.
If you're given a two by two matrix
describing a linear transformation
and some specific vector and you wanna know
where that linear transformation
takes that vector,
you can take the coordinates of the vector,
multiply them by the corresponding columns of the
matrix, then add together what you get.
This corresponds with the idea of adding the
scaled versions of our new basis vectors.
Let's see what this looks like in the
most general case where your matrix has entries
a, b, c, d.
And remember, this matrix is just a way
of packaging the information needed to describe a
linear transformation.
Always remember to interpret that first column a
c as the place where the first basis
vector lands and that second column b d
as the place where the second basis vector
lands.
When we apply this transformation to some vector
x y, what do you get?
Well, it'll be x times a c plus
y times b d.
Putting this together, you get a vector a
x plus b y, c x plus d
y.
You could even define this as matrix vector
multiplication
when you put the matrix on the left
of the vector like it's a function.
Then you could make high schoolers memorize this
without showing them the crucial part that makes
it feel intuitive.
But isn't it more fun to think about
these columns as the transformed versions of your
basis vectors and to think about the results
as the appropriate linear combination of those vectors?
Let's practice describing a few linear transformations with
matrices.
For example, if we rotate all of space
90 degrees counterclockwise,
then I hat lands on the coordinates zero,
one,
and j hat lands on the coordinates negative
one, zero.
So the matrix we end up with has
columns zero, one, negative one, zero.
To figure out what happens to any vector
after a 90 degree rotation, you could just
multiply its coordinates by this matrix.
Here's a fun transformation with a special name
called a shear.
In it, I hat remains fixed, so the
first column of the matrix is one zero,
but j hat moves over to the coordinates
one one, which become the second column of
the matrix.
And at the risk of being redundant here,
figuring out how a shear transforms a given
vector comes down to multiplying this matrix by
that vector.
Let's say we wanna go the other way
around, starting with a matrix, say with columns
one two and three one, and we wanna
deduce what its transformation looks like. Pause and
take a moment to see if you can
imagine it.
One way to do this is to first
move I hat to one two,
then move j hat to three one,
always moving the rest of space in such
a way that keeps grid lines parallel and
evenly spaced.
If the vectors that I hat and j
hat land on are linearly dependent,
which if you recall from last video means
that one is a scaled version of the
other, it means that the linear transformation
squishes all of two d space onto the
line where those two vectors sit, also known
as the one dimensional span of those two
linearly dependent vectors.
To sum up, linear transformations are a way
to move around space such that grid lines
remain parallel and evenly spaced and such that
the origin remains fixed. Delightfully,
these transformations can be described using only a
handful of numbers, the coordinates of where each
basis vector lands.
Matrices give us a language to describe these
transformations
where the columns represent those coordinates, and matrix
vector multiplication
is just a way to compute what that
transformation does to a given vector.
The important takeaway here is that every time
you see a matrix, you can interpret it
as a certain transformation of space.
Once you really digest this idea, you're in
a great position to understand linear algebra deeply.
Almost all of the topics coming up, from
matrix multiplication to determinants,
change of basis, eigenvalues,
all of these will become easier to understand
once you start thinking about matrices as transformations
of space.
Most immediately, in the next video, I'll be
talking about multiplying two matrices together. See you
then.