In the last video, along with the ideas
of vector addition and scalar multiplication,
I described vector coordinates,
where there's this back and forth between, for
example, pairs of numbers and two dimensional vectors.
Now, I imagine the vector coordinates were already
familiar to a lot of you, but there's
another kind of interesting way to think about
these coordinates, which is pretty central to linear
algebra.
When you have a pair of numbers that's
meant to describe a vector, like three, negative
two, I want you to think about each
coordinate as a scalar, meaning think about how
each one stretches or squishes vectors.
In the x y coordinate system, there are
two very special vectors.
The one pointing to the right with length
one, commonly called I hat or the unit
vector in the x direction, and the one
pointing straight up with length one, commonly called
j hat or the unit vector in the
y direction.
Now think of the x coordinate of our
vector as a scalar that scales I hat,
stretching it by a factor of three, and
the y coordinate as a scalar that scales
j hat, flipping it and stretching it by
a factor of two.
In this sense, the vector that these coordinates
describe is the sum of two scaled vectors.
That's a surprisingly important concept, this idea of
adding together two scaled vectors.
Those two vectors, I hat and j hat,
have a special name by the way. Together,
they're called the basis of a coordinate system.
What this means basically is that when you
think about coordinates as scalars, the basis vectors
are what those scalars actually, you know, scale.
There's also a more technical definition, but I'll
get to that later.
By framing our coordinate system in terms of
these two special basis vectors,
it raises a pretty interesting and subtle point.
We could have chosen different basis vectors and
gotten a completely reasonable new coordinate system.
For example, take some vector pointing up and
to the right along with some other vector
pointing down and to the right in some
way. Take a moment to think about all
the different vectors that you can get by
choosing two scalars,
using each one to scale one of the
vectors, then adding together what you get.
Which two dimensional vectors can you reach by
altering the choices of scalars?
The answer is that you can reach every
possible two dimensional vector and I think it's
a good puzzle to contemplate why.
A new pair of basis vectors like this
still gives us a valid way to go
back and forth between pairs of numbers and
two dimensional vectors,
but the association is definitely different from the
one that you get using the more standard
basis of I hat and j hat. This
is something I'll go into much more detail
on later, describing the exact relationship between different
coordinate systems.
But for right now, I just want you
to appreciate the fact that anytime we describe
vectors numerically,
it depends on an implicit choice of what
basis vectors we're using.
So anytime that you're scaling two vectors and
adding them like this, it's called a linear
combination
of those two vectors.
Where does this word linear come from? Why
does this have anything to do with lines?
Well, this isn't the etymology, but one way
I like to think about it is that
if you fix one of those scalars and
let the other one change its value freely,
the tip of the resulting vector draws a
straight line.
Now, if you let both scalars range freely
and consider every possible vector that you can
get, there are two things that can happen.
For most pairs of vectors, you'll be able
to reach every possible point in the plane.
Every two dimensional vector is within your grasp.
However, in the unlucky case where your two
original vectors happen to line up, the tip
of the resulting vector is limited to just
this single line passing through the origin.
Actually, technically there's a third possibility too. Both
your vectors could be zero, in which case
you'd just be stuck at the origin.
Here's some more terminology.
The set of all possible vectors that you
can reach with a linear combination of a
given pair of vectors is called the span
of those two vectors.
So restating what we just saw in this
lingo, the span of most pairs of two
d vectors is all vectors of two d
space. But when they line up, their span
is all vectors whose tip sit on a
certain line.
Remember how I said that linear algebra revolves
around vector addition and scalar multiplication?
Well, the span of two vectors is basically
a way of asking what are all the
possible vectors you can reach using only these
two fundamental operations,
vector addition and scalar multiplication.
This is a good time to talk about
how people commonly think about vectors as points.
It gets really crowded to think about a
whole collection of vectors sitting on a line
and more crowded still to think about all
two dimensional vectors all at once filling up
the plane.
So, when dealing with collections of vectors like
this, it's common to represent each one with
just a point in space.
The point at the tip of that vector
where, as usual, I want you thinking about
that vector with its tail on the origin.
That way, if you want to think about
every possible vector whose tip sits on a
certain line, just think about the line itself.
Likewise, to think about all possible two dimensional
vectors all at once, conceptualize
each one as the point where its tip
sits. So, effect, what you'll be thinking about
is the infinite flat sheet of two dimensional
space itself, leaving the arrows out of it.
In general, if you're thinking about a vector
on its own, think of it as an
arrow.
And if you're dealing with a collection of
vectors, it's convenient to think of them all
as points.
So, for our span example, the span of
most pairs of vectors ends up being the
entire infinite sheet of two dimensional space.
But, if they line up, their span is
just a line.
The idea of span gets a lot more
interesting if we start thinking about vectors in
three-dimensional
space.
For example, if you take two vectors in
three d space that are not pointing in
the same direction,
what does it mean to take their span?
Well, their span is the collection of all
possible linear combinations
of those two vectors. Meaning,
all possible vectors you get by scaling each
of the two of them in some way
and then adding them together.
You can kind of imagine turning two different
knobs to change the two scalars defining the
linear combination, adding the scaled vectors and following
the tip of the resulting vector.
That tip will trace out some kind of
flat sheet cutting through the origin of three-dimensional
space.
This flat sheet is the span of the
two vectors,
or more precisely, the set of all possible
vectors whose tips sit on that flat sheet
is the span of your two vectors.
Isn't that a beautiful mental image?
So, what happens if we add a third
vector and consider the span of all three
of those guys?
A linear combination of three vectors is defined
pretty much the same way as it is
for two. You'll choose three different scalars,
scale each of those vectors, and then add
them all together.
And again, the span of these vectors is
the set of all possible linear combinations.
Two different things could happen here. If your
third vector happens to be sitting on the
span of the first two,
then the span doesn't change. You're sort of
trapped on that same flat sheet. In other
words, adding a scaled version of that third
vector to the linear combination
doesn't really give you access to any new
vectors.
But if you just randomly choose a third
vector, it's almost certainly not sitting on the
span of those first two.
Then, since it's pointing in a separate direction,
it unlocks access to every possible three-dimensional vector.
One way I like to think about this
is that as you scale that new third
vector, it moves around that span sheet of
the first two, sweeping it through all of
space.
Another way to think about it is that
you're making full use of the three freely
changing scalars you have at your disposal to
access the full three dimensions of space.
Now, in the case where the third vector
was already sitting on the span of the
first two, or the case where two vectors
happen to line up, we want some terminology
to describe the fact that at least one
of these vectors is redundant, not adding anything
to our span.
Whenever this happens, where you have multiple vectors
and you could remove one without reducing the
span, the relevant terminology is to say that
they are linearly dependent.
Another way of phrasing that would be to
say that one of the vectors can be
expressed as a linear combination of the others
since it's already in the span of the
others.
On the other hand, if each vector really
does add another dimension to the span, they're
said to be linearly independent.
So, with all of that terminology, and hopefully
with some good mental images to go with
it, let me leave you with a puzzle
before we go. The technical definition of a
basis of a space is a set of
linearly independent vectors that span that space.
Now, given how I described a basis earlier,
and given your current understanding of the words
span and linearly independent,
think about why this definition would make sense.
In the next video, I'll get into matrices
in transforming space. See you then.