Hey everyone, where we last left off I
showed what linear transformations look like and how
to represent them using matrices.
This is worth a quick recap because it's
just really important, but of course if this
feels like more than just a recap go
back and watch the full video.
Technically speaking, linear transformations are functions with vectors
as inputs and vectors as outputs. But I
showed last time how we can think about
them visually as smooshing around space in such
a way that grid lines stay parallel and
evenly spaced, and so that the origin remains
fixed.
The key takeaway was that a linear transformation
is completely determined by where it takes the
basis vectors of the space, which for two
dimensions means I hat and j hat.
This is because any other vector could be
described as a linear combination
of those basis vectors.
A vector with coordinates is
x times I hat plus y times j
hat.
After going through the transformation,
this property that grid lines remain parallel and
evenly spaced has a wonderful consequence.
The place where your vector lands will be
x times the transformed version of I hat
plus y times the transformed version of j
hat.
This means if you keep a record of
the coordinates where I hat lands and the
coordinates where j hat lands, you can compute
that a vector which starts at x y
must land on x times the new coordinates
of I hat plus y times the new
coordinates of j hat.
The convention is to record the coordinates of
where I hat and j hat land as
the columns of a matrix
and to define this sum of the scaled
versions of those columns by x and y
to be matrix vector multiplication.
In this way, a matrix represents a specific
linear transformation and multiplying a matrix by a
vector is what it means computationally
to apply that transformation
to that vector.
Alright. Recap over. On to the new stuff.
Oftentimes, you find yourself wanting to describe the
effects of applying one transformation
and then another.
For example, maybe you wanna describe what happens
when you first rotate the plane 90 degrees
counterclockwise
then apply a shear.
The overall effect here from start to finish
is another linear transformation
distinct from the rotation and the shear.
This new linear transformation is commonly called the
composition
of the two separate transformations we applied.
And like any linear transformation,
it can be described with a matrix all
of its own by following I hat and
j hat.
In this example,
the ultimate landing spot for I hat after
both transformations
is one one. So let's make that the
first column of a matrix.
Likewise, j hat ultimately ends up at the
location negative one zero, so we make that
the second column of the matrix.
This new matrix captures the overall effect of
applying a rotation then a shear, but as
one single action rather than two successive ones.
Here's one way to think about that new
matrix. If you were to take some vector
and pump it through the rotation then the
shear,
the long way to compute where it ends
up is to first multiply it on the
left by the rotation matrix,
then take whatever you get and multiply that
on the left by the shear matrix.
This is numerically speaking what it means to
apply a rotation then a shear to a
given vector.
But whatever you get should be the same
as just applying this new composition matrix that
we just found by that same vector,
no matter what vector you chose. Since this
new matrix is supposed to capture the same
overall effect as the rotation then shear action.
Based on how things are written down here,
I think it's reasonable to call this new
matrix the product of the original two matrices.
Don't you?
We can think about how to compute that
product more generally in just a moment, but
it's way too easy to get lost in
the forest of numbers. Always remember that multiplying
two matrices like this has the geometric meaning
of applying one transformation
then another.
One thing that's kinda weird here is that
this has us reading from right to left.
You first apply the transformation represented by the
matrix on the right, then you apply the
transformation represented by the matrix on the left.
This stems from function notation since we write
functions on the left of variables. So every
time you compose two functions, you always have
to read it right to left. Good news
for the Hebrew readers, bad news for the
rest of us.
Let's look at another example.
Take the matrix with columns one one and
negative two zero whose transformation looks like this,
and let's call it m one.
Next, take the matrix with columns zero one
and two zero whose transformation looks like this
and let's call that guy m two.
The total effect of applying m one then
m two gives us a new transformation.
So let's find its matrix.
But this time, let's see if we can
do it without watching the animations
and instead just using the numerical entries in
each matrix.
First, we need to figure out where I
hat goes.
After applying m one, the new coordinates of
I hat by definition
are given by that first column of m
one, namely one one.
To see what happens after applying m two,
multiply the matrix for m two by that
vector one one.
Working it out the way that I described
last video, you'll get the vector two one.
This will be the first column of the
composition matrix.
Likewise, to follow j hat, the second column
of m one tells us that it first
lands on negative two zero.
Then when we apply m two to that
vector,
you can work out the matrix vector product
to get zero negative two,
which becomes the second column of our composition
matrix.
Let me talk through that same process again,
but this time I'll show variable entries in
each matrix just to show that the same
line of reasoning works for any matrices.
This is more symbol heavy and will require
some more room, but it should be pretty
satisfying for anyone who has previously been taught
matrix multiplication the more rote way.
To follow where I hat goes, start by
looking at the first column of the matrix
on the right since this is where I
hat initially lands.
Multiplying that column by the matrix on the
left is how you can tell where the
intermediate version of I hat ends up after
applying the second transformation.
So the first column of the composition matrix
will always equal the left matrix times the
first column of the right matrix.
Likewise,
j hat will always initially land on the
second column of the right matrix.
So multiplying the left matrix by this second
column will give its final location and hence
that's the second column of the composition matrix.
Notice, there's a lot of symbols here and
it's common to be taught this formula as
something to memorize along with a certain algorithmic
process to kind of help remember it. But
I really do think that before memorizing that
process you should get in the habit of
thinking about what matrix multiplication really represents,
applying one transformation after another.
Trust me, this will give you a much
better conceptual framework that makes the properties of
matrix multiplication
much easier to understand.
For example, here's a question. Does it matter
what order we put the two matrices in
when we multiply them?
Well, let's think through a simple example like
the one from earlier.
Take a shear which fixes I hat and
smooshes j hat over to the right and
a 90 degree rotation.
If you first do the shear then rotate,
we can see that I hat ends up
at zero one and j hat ends up
at negative one one, both are generally pointing
close together.
If you first rotate then do the shear,
I hat ends up over at one one
and j hat is often a different direction
at negative one zero and they're pointing, you
know, farther apart.
The overall effect here is clearly different. So
evidently order totally does matter.
Notice, by thinking in terms of transformations,
that's the kind of thing that you can
do in your head by visualizing.
No matrix multiplication necessary.
I remember when I first took linear algebra,
there was this one homework problem that asked
us to prove that matrix multiplication
is associative.
This means that if you have three matrices,
a, b, and c, and you multiply them
all together, it shouldn't matter if you first
compute a times b, then multiply the result
by c, or if you first multiply b
times c, then multiply that result by a
on the left. In other words, it doesn't
matter where you put the parentheses.
Now, if you try to work through this
numerically like I did back then, it's horrible,
just horrible, and unenlightening for that matter. But
when you think about matrix multiplication as applying
one transformation after another,
this property is just trivial.
Can you see why?
What it's saying is that if you first
apply c then b then a, it's the
same as applying c then b then a.
I mean, there's nothing to prove. You're just
applying the same three things one after the
other, all in the same order.
This might feel like cheating, but it's not.
This is an honest to goodness proof that
matrix multiplication is associative.
And even better than that, it's a good
explanation for why that property should be true.
I really do encourage you to play around
more with this idea, imagining two different transformations,
thinking about what happens when you apply one
after the other, and then working out the
matrix product numerically.
Trust me, this is the kind of playtime
that really makes the idea sink in.
In the next video, I'll start talking about
extending these ideas beyond just two dimensions. See
you then.