Hello hello again. So moving forward I'll be
assuming that you have a visual understanding of
linear transformations and how they're represented with matrices,
the way that I've been talking about in
the last few videos.
If you think about a couple of these
linear transformations
you might notice how some of them seem
to stretch space out while others squish it
on in.
One thing that turns out to be pretty
useful for understanding one of these transformations is
to measure exactly how much it stretches or
squishes things.
More specifically,
to measure the factor by which the area
of a given region increases
or decreases.
For example, look at the matrix with columns
three zero and zero two. It scales I
hat by a factor of three and scales
j hat by a factor of two.
Now, if we focus our attention on the
one by one square whose bottom sits on
I hat and whose left side sits on
j hat, after the transformation this turns into
a two by three rectangle.
Since this region started out with area one
and ended up with area six,
we can say the linear transformation
has scaled its area by a factor of
six.
Compare that to a shear whose matrix has
columns one zero and one one, meaning I
hat stays in place and j hat moves
over to one one.
That same unit square determined by I hat
and j hat gets slanted and turned into
a parallelogram,
but the area of that parallelogram is still
one since its base and height each continue
to have length one.
So even though this transformation smooshes things about,
it seems to leave areas unchanged, at least
in the case of that one unit square.
Actually, though, if you know how much the
area of that one single unit square changes,
it can tell you how the area of
any possible region in space changes.
For starters, notice that whatever happens to one
square in the grid has to happen to
any other square in the grid no matter
the size.
This follows from the fact that grid lines
remain parallel and evenly spaced.
Then any shape that's not a grid square
can be approximated by grid squares pretty well
with arbitrarily good approximations if you use small
enough grid squares.
So since the areas of all those tiny
grid squares are being scaled by some single
amount, the area of the blob as a
whole will also be scaled by that same
single amount.
This very special scaling factor, the factor by
which a linear transformation changes any area,
is called the determinant of that transformation.
I'll show how to compute the determinant of
a transformation using its matrix later on in
this video, but understanding what it represents is,
trust me, much more important than the computation.
For example, the determinant of a transformation would
be three if that transformation
increases the area of a region by a
factor of three.
The determinant of a transformation would be half
if it squishes down all areas by a
factor of half.
And the determinant of a two d transformation
is zero if it squishes all of space
onto a line or even onto a single
point since then the area of any region
would become zero.
That last example will prove to be pretty
important. It means that checking if the determinant
of a given matrix is zero will give
a way of computing whether or not the
transformation associated with that matrix squishes everything into
a smaller dimension.
You'll see in the next few videos why
this is even a useful thing to think
about, but for now I just wanna lay
down all of the visual intuition,
which in and of itself is a beautiful
thing to think about.
Okay. I need to confess that what I've
said so far is not quite right. The
full concept of the determinant allows for negative
values.
But what would the idea of scaling an
area by a negative amount even mean?
This has to do with the idea of
orientation.
For example, notice how this transformation
gives the sensation of flipping space over.
If you were thinking of two d space
as a sheet of paper, a transformation like
that one seems to turn over that sheet
onto the other side.
Any transformations that do this are said to
invert the orientation of space.
Another way to think about it is in
terms of I hat and j hat. Notice
that in their starting positions j hat is
to the left of I hat.
If after a transformation j hat is now
on the right of I hat, the orientation
of space has been inverted.
Whenever this happens, whenever the orientation of space
is inverted, the determinant will be negative.
The absolute value of the determinant though still
tells you the factor by which areas have
been scaled.
For example, the matrix with columns one one
and two negative one encodes a transformation that
has determinant, I'll just tell you negative three.
And what this means is that space gets
flipped over and areas are scaled by a
factor of three.
So why would this idea of a negative
area scaling factor be a natural way to
describe orientation flipping?
Think about the series of transformations you get
by slowly letting I hat get closer and
closer to j hat. As I hat gets
closer, all of the areas in space are
getting squished more and more, meaning the determinant
approaches zero.
Once I hat lines up perfectly with j
hat, the determinant is zero.
Then if I hat continues the way that
it was going, doesn't it kind of feel
natural for the determinant to keep decreasing into
the negative numbers?
So that's the understanding of determinants in two
dimensions.
What do you think it should mean for
three dimensions?
It also tells you how much a transformation
scales things, but this time it tells you
how much volumes get scaled.
Just as in two dimensions where this is
easiest to think about by focusing on one
particular square with an area one and watching
only what happens to it, In three dimensions,
it helps to focus your attention on the
specific one by one by one cube whose
edges are resting on the basis vectors I
hat, j hat, and k hat.
After the transformation,
that cube might get warped into some kind
of slanty slanty cube.
This shape, by the way, has the best
name ever, parallelepiped,
a name that's made even more delightful when
your professor has a nice thick Russian accent.
Since this cube starts out with a volume
of one and the determinant gives the factor
by which any volume is scaled, you can
think of the determinant simply as being the
volume of that parallelepiped
that the cube turns into.
A determinant of zero would mean that all
of space is squished onto something with zero
volume,
meaning either a flat plane, a line, or
in the most extreme case, onto a single
point.
Those of you who watch chapter two will
recognize this as meaning that the columns of
the matrix are linearly dependent.
Can you see why?
What about negative determinants? What should that mean
for three dimensions?
One way to describe orientation in three d
is with the right hand rule.
Point the forefinger of your right hand in
the direction of I hat, stick out your
middle finger in the direction of j hat,
and notice how when you point your thumb
up it's in the direction of k hat.
If you can still do that after the
transformation
orientation has not changed and the determinant is
positive.
Otherwise,
if after the transformation it only makes sense
to do that with your left hand orientation
has been flipped and the determinant is negative.
So if you haven't seen it before, you're
probably wondering by now how do you actually
compute the determinant?
For a two by two matrix with entries
a, b, c, d, the formula is a
times d minus b times c.
Here's part of an intuition for where this
formula comes from. Let's say that the terms
b and c both happened to be zero.
Then the term a tells you how much
I hat is stretched in the x direction
and the term d tells you how much
j hat is stretched in the y direction.
So since those other terms are zero, it
should make sense that a times d gives
the area of the rectangle that our favorite
unit square turns into, kinda like the 3,002
example from earlier.
Even if only one of b or c
are zero, you'll have a parallelogram
with a base a and a height d,
so the area should still be a times
d.
Loosely speaking, if both b and c are
nonzero,
then that b times c term tells you
how much this parallelogram
is stretched or squished in the diagonal direction.
For those of you hungry for a more
precise description of this b times c term,
here's a helpful diagram if you'd like to
pause and ponder.
Now if you feel like computing determinants by
hand is something that you need to know,
the only way to get it down is
to just practice it with a few. There's
really not that much I can say or
animate that's gonna drill in the computation.
This is all triply true for three-dimensional determinants.
There is a formula and if you feel
like that's something you need to know, you
should practice with a few matrices or, you
know, go watch Sal Khan work through a
few.
Honestly though, I don't think that those computations
fall within the essence of linear algebra, but
I definitely think that understanding what the determinant
represents falls within that essence.
Here's kind of a fun question to think
about before the next video. If you multiply
two matrices together,
the determinant of the resulting matrix is the
same as the product of the determinants of
the original two matrices.
If you tried to justify this with numbers,
it would take a really long time, but
see if you can explain why this makes
sense in just one sentence.
Next up, I'll be relating the idea of
linear transformations covered so far to one of
the areas where linear algebra is most useful:
linear systems of equations. See you then!