Hey folks. I've got a relatively quick video
for you today, just sort of a footnote
between chapters.
In the last two videos, I talked about
linear transformations and matrices,
but I only showed the specific case of
transformations that take two dimensional vectors to other
two dimensional vectors.
In general throughout the series, we'll work mainly
in two dimensions,
mostly because it's easier to actually see on
the screen and wrap your mind around. But
more importantly than that, once you get all
the core ideas in two dimensions, they carry
over pretty seamlessly to higher dimensions.
Nevertheless, it's good to peek our heads outside
of flat land now and then to, you
know, see what it means to apply these
ideas in more than just those two dimensions.
For example, consider a linear transformation
with three-dimensional vectors as inputs and three-dimensional vectors
as outputs.
We can visualize this by smooshing around all
the points in three-dimensional space as represented by
a grid in such a way that keeps
the grid lines parallel and evenly spaced and
which fixes the origin in place.
And just as with two dimensions, every point
of space that we see moving around is
really just a proxy for a vector who
has its tip at that point. And what
we're really doing is thinking about input vectors
moving over to their corresponding outputs.
And just as with two dimensions,
one of these transformations is completely described by
where the basis vectors go.
But now, there are three standard basis vectors
that we typically use. The unit vector in
the x direction, I hat, the unit vector
in the y direction, j hat, and a
new guy, the unit vector in the z
direction called k hat.
In fact, I think it's easier to think
about these transformations by only following those basis
vectors since the full three d grid representing
all points can get kinda messy.
By leaving a copy of the original axes
in the background, we can think about the
coordinates of where each of these three basis
vectors lands.
Record the coordinates of these three vectors as
the columns of a three by three matrix.
This gives a matrix that completely describes the
transformation
using only nine numbers.
As a simple example, consider the transformation that
rotates space 90 degrees around the y axis.
So that would mean that it takes I
hat to the coordinates zero zero negative one
on the z axis.
It doesn't move j hat, so it stays
at the coordinates zero one zero, and then
k hat moves over to the x axis
at one zero zero.
Those three sets of coordinates become the columns
of a matrix that describes that rotation transformation.
To see where a vector with coordinates x
y z lands, the reasoning is almost identical
to what it was for two dimensions.
Each of those coordinates can be thought of
as instructions
for how to scale each basis vector so
that they add together to get your vector.
And the important part, just like the two
d case, is that this scaling and adding
process works both before and after the transformation.
So to see where your vector lands, you
multiply those coordinates by the corresponding columns of
the matrix, and then you add together the
three results.
Multiplying two matrices is also similar. Whenever you
see two three by three matrices getting multiplied
together, you should imagine first applying the transformation
encoded by the right one,
then applying the transformation encoded by the left
one.
It turns out that three d matrix multiplication
is actually pretty important for fields like computer
graphics and robotics since things like rotations and
three dimensions can be pretty hard to describe,
but they're easier to wrap your mind around
if you can break them down as the
composition of separate easier to think about rotations.
Performing this matrix multiplication numerically is once again
pretty similar to the two dimensional case.
In fact, a good way to test your
understanding of the last video would be to
try to reason through what specifically this matrix
multiplication should look like, thinking closely about how
it relates to the idea of applying two
successive transformations in space.
In the next video, I'll start getting into
the determinant.