The fundamental root of it all building block
for linear algebra is the vector. So it's
worth making sure that we're all on the
same page about what exactly a vector is.
You see, broadly speaking, there are three distinct
but related ideas about vectors, which I'll call
the physics student perspective, the computer science student
perspective, and the mathematician's perspective.
The physics student perspective is that vectors are
arrows pointing in space.
What defines a given vector is its length
and the direction it's pointing. But as long
as those two facts are the same, you
can move it all around and it's still
the same vector.
Vectors that live in the flat plane are
two dimensional, and those sitting in broader space
that you and I live in are three-dimensional.
The computer science perspective is that vectors are
ordered lists of numbers.
For example, let's say you were doing some
analytics about house prices and the only features
you cared about were square footage and price.
You might model each house with a pair
of numbers, the first indicating square footage and
the second indicating price.
Notice the order matters here.
In the lingo, you'd be modeling houses as
two dimensional vectors where in this context vector
is pretty much just a fancy word for
list and what makes it two dimensional is
the fact that the length of that list
is two.
The mathematician, on the other hand, seeks to
generalize both these views, basically saying that a
vector can be anything where there's a sensible
notion of adding two vectors and multiplying a
vector by a number, operations that I'll talk
about later on in this video.
The details of this view are rather abstract,
and I actually think it's healthy to ignore
it until the last video of this series
favoring a more concrete setting in the interim.
But the reason I bring it up here
is that it hints at the fact that
the ideas of vector addition and multiplication by
numbers will play an important role throughout linear
algebra.
But before I talk about those operations, let's
just settle in on a specific thought to
have in mind when I say the word
vector.
Given the geometric focus that I'm shooting for
here, whenever I introduce a new topic involving
vectors, I want you to first think about
an arrow and specifically
think about that arrow inside a coordinate system
like the x y plane with its tail
sitting at the origin.
This is a little bit different from the
physics student perspective where vectors can freely sit
anywhere they want in space. In linear algebra,
it's almost always the case that your vector
will be rooted at the origin.
Then, once you understand a new concept in
the context of arrows in space,
we'll translate it over to the list of
numbers point of view, which we can do
by considering the coordinates of the vector.
Now, while I'm sure that many of you
are already familiar with this coordinate system, it's
worth walking through explicitly since this is where
all of the important back and forth happens
between the two perspectives of linear algebra.
Focusing our attention on two dimensions for the
moment, you have a horizontal line called the
x axis and a vertical line called the
y axis.
The place where they intersect is called the
origin, which you should think of as the
center of space and the root of all
vectors.
After choosing an arbitrary length to represent one,
you make tick marks on each axis to
represent this distance.
When I want to convey the idea of
two d space as a whole, which you'll
see comes up a lot in these videos,
I'll extend these tick marks to make grid
lines. But right now, they'll actually get a
little bit in the way.
The coordinates of a vector is a pair
of numbers that basically gives instructions for how
to get from the tail of that vector
at the origin to its tip.
The first number tells you how far to
walk along the x axis, positive numbers indicating
rightward motion, negative numbers indicating leftward motion, and
the second number tells you how far to
walk parallel to the y axis after that.
Positive numbers indicating upward motion and negative numbers
indicating downward motion.
To distinguish vectors from points, the convention is
to write this pair of numbers vertically with
square brackets around them.
Every pair of numbers gives you one and
only one vector,
and every vector is associated with one and
only one pair of numbers.
What about in three dimensions?
Well, you add a third axis called the
z axis, which is perpendicular to both the
x and y axis
and in this case each vector is associated
with an ordered triplet of numbers. The first
tells you how far to move along the
x axis, the second tells you how far
to move parallel to the y axis, and
the third one tells you how far to
then move parallel to this new z axis.
Every triplet of numbers gives you one unique
vector in space,
and every vector in space gives you exactly
one triplet of numbers.
Alright, so back to vector addition and multiplication
by numbers. After all, every topic in linear
algebra is going to center around these two
operations.
Luckily, each one's pretty straightforward to define.
Let's say we have two vectors, one pointing
up and a little to the right and
the other one pointing right and down a
bit. To add these two vectors, move the
second one so that its tail sits at
the tip of the first one.
Then, if you draw a new vector from
the tail of the first one to where
the tip of the second one now sits,
that new vector is their sum.
This definition of addition, by the way, is
pretty much the only time in linear algebra
where we let vectors stray away from the
origin.
Now, why is this a reasonable thing to
do? Why this definition of addition and not
some other one?
Well, the way I like to think about
it is that each vector represents a certain
movement, a step with a certain distance and
direction in space.
If you take a step along the first
vector,
then take a step in the direction and
distance described by the second vector, the overall
effect is just the same as if you
moved along the sum of those two vectors
to start with.
You could think about this as an extension
of how we think about adding numbers on
a number line.
One way that we teach kids to think
about this, say with two plus five, is
to think of moving two steps to the
right followed by another five steps to the
right. The overall effect is the same as
if you just took seven steps to the
right.
In fact, let's see how vector addition looks
numerically.
The first vector here has coordinates one, two,
and the second one has coordinates three, negative
one.
When you take the vector sum using this
tip to tail method, you can think of
a four step path from the origin to
the tip of the second vector. Walk one
to the right, then two up, then three
to the right, then one down.
Reorganizing these steps so that you first do
all of the rightward motion, then do all
the vertical motion, you can read it as
saying, first move one plus three to the
right, then move two minus one up.
So the new vector has coordinates one plus
three and two plus negative one.
In general, vector addition in this list of
numbers conception
looks like matching up their terms and adding
each one together.
The other fundamental vector operation is multiplication by
a number. Now, is best understood just by
looking at a few examples.
If you take the number two and multiply
it by a given vector,
it means you stretch out that vector so
that it's two times as long as when
you started.
If you multiply that vector by say one
third, it means you squish it down so
that it's one third the original length.
When you multiply it by a negative number,
like negative 1.8,
then the vector first gets flipped around, then
stretched out by that factor of 1.8.
This process of stretching or squishing or sometimes
reversing the direction of a vector is called
scaling.
And whenever you catch a number like two
or one third or negative 1.8 acting like
this, scaling some vector,
you call it a scalar.
In fact, throughout linear algebra, one of the
main things that numbers do is scale vectors.
So it's common to use the word scalar
pretty much interchangeably with the word number.
Numerically, stretching out a vector by a factor
of say two corresponds with multiplying each of
its components by that factor two.
So in the conception of vectors as lists
of numbers,
multiplying a given vector by a scalar means
multiplying each one of those components by that
scalar.
You'll see in the following videos what I
mean when I say that linear algebra topics
tend to revolve around these two fundamental operations,
vector addition and scalar multiplication.
And I'll talk more in the last video
about how and why the mathematician thinks only
about these operations independent and abstracted away from
however you choose to represent vectors.
In truth, it doesn't matter whether you think
about vectors as fundamentally being arrows in space,
like I'm suggesting you do, that happen to
have a nice numerical representation,
or fundamentally as lists of numbers that happen
to have a nice geometric interpretation.
The usefulness of linear algebra has less to
do with either one of these views than
it does with the ability to translate back
and forth between them. It gives the data
analyst a nice way to conceptualize many lists
of numbers in a visual way which can
seriously clarify patterns in data and give a
global view of what certain operations do. And
on the flip side, it gives people like
physicists and computer graphics programmers a language to
describe space and the manipulation of space using
numbers that can be crunched and run through
a computer.
When I do mathy animations, for example, I
start by thinking about what's actually going on
in space and then get the computer to
represent things numerically,
thereby figuring out where to place the pixels
on the screen. And doing that usually relies
on a lot of linear algebra understanding.
So there are your vector basics, and in
the next video, I'll start getting into some
pretty neat concepts surrounding vectors like span, bases,
and linear dependence. See you then.